Faiza Rashid

fayezaarashid@gmail.com | https://azaif7.github.io/ | (647) 467-3193 | Toronto, ON

SUMMARY

Driven, flexible, dedicated, collaborating and highly skilled Front-End Developer with 5+ years of experience building robust, complex, and accessible user interfaces and applications with strong background in capital markets, web technologies, web development, responsive design, React, Redux, JavaScript, TypeScript, HTML and CSS.

HIGHLIGHTS

- Hands-on experience in ReactJS, TypeScript, JavaScript and CSS
- AXIOS get, post, put and delete requests
- Responsive web design
- Redux, React Router
- React testing library, manual debugging
- Website optimization techniques
- REST API integration
- HTML5, JSX
- Version Control: Git, GitHub
- Agile development, SCRUM
- Software development life cycle, waterfall
- CSS, SCSS, Bootstrap, React Bootstrap, Tailwind CSS
- Experience with front-end built tools, such as Webpack.
- SEO optimization
- Excellent communication skills
- Passion for learning and teaching others and thrives in fast paced environment
- Good understanding of OOP's core pillars, experience building progressive and hybrid applications
- Strong Problem-Solving skills
- Reliable, productive and able to write clean and efficient code, debug and troubleshoot any bugs that may arise

DEVELOPMENT TOOLS

Software/Languages: Visual Studio Code, Figma, Lucid Charts, Postman, PhpMyAdmin,

Wordpress, SCRUM **Database:** MySQL Server

Operating Systems: Windows 10, 11, XP/7, MacOS

Other tools: MS Office, Selenium Web, Google Dev Tools

Web Development: HTML5, CSS3, Tailwind CSS, Bootstrap 4 & 5, JavaScript, jQuery, React.js,

Redux, Axios, Typescript

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer - Front End Troon Technologies, Pakistan, April 2020-April 2023

- Developed and maintained responsive, high-performance software applications targeting mobile devices and desktop clients in software development
- Utilized modern frontend technologies such as **React.js**, **Typescript**, HTML5, SCSS and JSON to create user-friendly web pages
- Implemented custom **React hooks**, **Redux**, and **Redux Toolkit** for efficient frontend development, including state management.
- Utilized Formik and React Forms library for building forms with client-side validation using Formik and Yup and server-side rendering using **Axios** library.
- NPM for package installation, react router for navigation through out the project
- Strong understanding of Virtual DOM and code refactoring and optimization
- Hands-on understanding of latest paradigms in Frontend Development such as State Management, Web sockets, Web components, Lazy Loading and bundle optimization (webpack)
- Integrated **RESTful APIs** to enhance functionality and user experience
- Worked collaboratively with teams, attending daily SCRUM meetings, sprint planning, and using project management tools like Teamwork and Github for version control while also conducting code reviews, writing tests (Jest and React testing libraries), and deploying bug-free sprints to production.

Lead Front-End Developer, SyntecX, Islamabad, Pakistan, January 2019-March 2020

- Built web applications using Angular 7+, HTML, CSS, SCSS and JavaScript
- Wrote clean, modular, high-performance, **reusable code**/ UI components/libraries
- Templates and reusable components in Angular and navigation using routes and router module from Angular router module
- Implemented responsive design and cross-browser compatibility using HTML5, CSS3 and Bootstrap 4 and 5
- Components and templates creation using **Angular 7+** and Typescript
- Client side validation using Angular forms and Restful API's integration using Axios library
- Used free tools like google trends to improve **SEO** and **JIRA** for project management
- Slick jquery library to create eye catching carousels
- Utilized **Git** for version control systems and collaborated effectively with team members
- Mentoring junior team members, collaborating with QA team to deliver bug free sprint

Front-End Developer, Ideofuzion, Islamabad. Pakistan, September 2017-December 2018

- Collaborate with web development team to design user interfaces for client websites using HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap 4 and 5, JavaScript ES6 and Angular
- Assisted in the design, development, and maintenance of **responsive**, high-performance web applications

- Daily ticket resolutions and time logging on JIRA and **Gitlab** for version control
- PSD/Figma/Zeplin prototypes to HTML conversion
- Slick library to create high end and eye catching carousels and Google recaptcha for verification
- Interface using Angular components and templates

EDUCATION

University of Science in Software Engineering BS, Software Engineering

July, 2017 Taxila, Pakistan

- Scholarship from university; 3.63/4.0 GPA
- Certificate of Excellence for the post of Arts and Decoration Head of SoftDesk society

Virtual University PGD, Computer Science

April, 2021 Islamabad, Pakistan

• 3.89/4.0 GPA

PROJECTS

RiskShark (https://riskshark.io)

- Developed RiskShark web app using React, Redux, HTML, SCSS and JavaScript.
- Developed reusable UI components using React Hooks and JSX.
- Collaborated with devops team to deploy the application on production

REFERENCES

Available upon request